FANSA KONE

University of Montreal (UdeM)
Department of Economics
3150 Jean Brillant Street, C6070-10
Montreal (Quebec, Canada), H3C 3J7

Email: fansa.francois.kone@umontreal.ca Citizenship: Ivorian and Canadian PR Phone: +1 514 561 3741

July 2, 2024

SUMMARY

I'm a PhD candidate in Economics with a quantitative background in Statistics. My research interests include Macroeconomics specifically Public Finance, International Trade, and Climate Change. Besides my technical strengths, I have excellent leadership and communication skills.

EDUCATION

University of Montreal, CIREQ

2019-

PhD candidate in Economics, Canada

Ecole Nationale Supérieure de Statistiques et d'Economie Appliquée (ENSEA) 2016-2019 MSc in Statistics and Economics (ISE) 2016-2019, Côte d'Ivoire

Institut National Polytechnique Félix Houphouet Boigny

2014-2016

Mathematics and commercial studies, Intensive two-years BSc program 2014-2016, Côte d'Ivoire

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research interest

Macroeconomics, Public Finance, International Trade, and Climate Change

Working papers

- Balanced Budget Rule and Economic Growth [Paper]
- \bullet Trade, Shocks Transmission, and Monetary Policy in a Regional Trade Agreement, with $R\acute{e}gis$ Kouassi

Research in progress

- Transition to Renewables and Public Debt Sustainability, with Lucien Chaffa and Kodjo Koudakpo
- Bridging Economies: Measuring Trade Potential Between Nations, with Régis Kouassi
- WAEMU facing AfCFTA: implications for trade and monetary policies, with Régis Kouassi

Policy papers/reports

- The effects of progressive personal income tax and targeted social assistance reforms on revenue collection, poverty, and occupations in Kazakhstan, with Mohamed Coulibaly, policy brief, UNICEF May 2024
- KAZAMOD (first microsimulation model in Kazakhstan) Country Report: 2022, with Mohamed Coulibaly, Yersultan Tamabekov, and Arman Umerbayev Kazakhstan, UNICEF May 2024
- Engendered Commitment to Equity (E-CEQ) in Guinea, with Mohamed Coulibaly, Aissatou Oue-draogo, and Kadidia Koné, World Bank

• Engendered Commitment to Equity (E-CEQ) in Togo, with Mohamed Coulibaly, Aissatou Oue-draoqo, and Kadidia Koné, World Bank

Academic Presentations

Africa Meeting of the Econometric Society (AFES), Abidjan, Côte d'Ivoire, June 2024

Canadian Economic Association, Winnipeg, June 2023

18th Ph.D. students CIREQ conference, Montreal, May 2023

Société Canadienne de Science économique, Québec city, Québec, May 2023

Quebec Social Sciences Ph.D. presentations group, Montreal-online, (September 2021, February 2022, October 2022, April 2023, January 2024)

Macroeconomics Workshop, lead by my advisor Guillaume Sublet (monthly presentations, since 2022-) International Conference of Statistics and Applied Economics (CISEA), July 2019, ENSEA, Abidjan Côte d'Ivoire

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

World Bank consultant

2022-present

Poverty and Equity Global Practice, World Bank

- Analysing the impact of the Russian's invasion of Ukraine on the well-being of households in Guinea
- Contributing to the development of the Engendered Commitment to Equity (E-CEQ) for Guinea and Togo;

UNICEF consultant

December 2023-May 2024

- Key Contributor to the development of the first tax benefit model based on EUROMOD methodology tailored for Kazakhstan (KAZAMOD)
- Trained government officials on using the built model KAZAMOD

Teaching 2021-

Initiation to economics (UdeM); Fall 2024, Fall 2023

Economics data analysis (UdeM); winter 2023

Initiation to economics (UdeM); Fall 2021 (Online, undergraduate level)

Teaching assistant

2020-

Advanced macroeconomics (UdeM); Winter 2022, 2023, 2024 (PhD level) for professor Guillaume Sublet Special topics in money and banking; Fall 2022, 2023 (graduate level) for professor René Garcia

North American economics (UdeM); Winter 2021, for professor Vasia Panousi

International Finance (UdeM); Fall 2020, for professor Emanuela Cardia

International trade (UdeM); Fall 2020, for professor Abraham HOLLANDER

Introduction to Microeconomics (Winter 2024)

Principles of economics (UdeM): Winter, Summer, Fall 2022 (Online, undergraduate)

Economics data analysis (UdeM); Fall 2021 (Online, undergraduate)

Introduction to macroeconomics (UdeM); Fall 2020, Winter 2021

AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

Fonds de Recherche du Québec Science et Culture (FRQSC) fellowships, ranked 2nd, 2022-2024

Ph.D. fellowships, Department of Economics, UdeM 2019-2023

Canadian Economics Association students travel grant, Winnipeg 2023

CIREQ students travel grant, SCSE conference in Quebec 2023

Tuition-fee Waiver Scholarship of Graduate Studies, University of Montreal, Canada, 2019-2021

Excellence Scolarship, Government of Côte d'Ivoire, high school and university scolarship (2011-2019)

Winner Public Forum Debate, with a team ENSEA (2019)

Awards "meilleure plume", Writing competition, ENSEA (2017)

Awards of the best scientist at high school level, received from the minister of education at Journée National du Mérite et de l'Excellence (JNMEX), Côte d'Ivoire, 2015

Awards of the best student of high school level at Lycée Mixte I de Yamoussoukro, Côte d'Ivoire, 2014

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Programming Stata, Python, Matlab, Latex Microsoft Excel, Powerpoint, Word

VOLUNTEERING ACTIVITIES AND TALKS

Talk at ENSEA to MSc Students from different Universities in Abidjan

June 2024

PhD in North America: Distinguishing Reality from Misconceptions

Talk to Students at INPHB, online

January 2024

Sharing my experience to help pupils and students find better educational paths

Economics PhD student's representative

Fall 2021-2023

Defending and representing PhD students' interests at UdeM, Canada

Talk to MSc Students at ENSEA

2021

Presenting PhD opportunities to Students at ENSEA

UdeM ambassador, (Fall 2019, Winter 2020), Passerelle (2020) and Passerelle + (2021)

Helped new students integrate Université of Montréal in the context of the pandemic, Canada

Division des Ingénieurs Statisticiens Economistes

2018-2019

President of "commission recherche emploi" facilitating students' integration into the labor market

ENSEA English Club

2017-2018

Organizing activities to help students at ENSEA improve their English skills, Côte d'Ivoire

LANGUAGE AND OTHER INTERESTS

French (native), English (fluent), soccer, reading, writing, badmington

ABSTRACT OF SOME SELECTED WORK IN PROGRESS

Balanced Budget Rule and Economic Growth

This paper studies the impact of a Balanced Budget rule (BBR) over the business cycle on economic growth, as adopted in Switzerland's constitution in 2003. First, using a synthetic control method, I find that over the 2003-2018 period, the BBR adoption has been associated with 0.95% higher yearly growth on average in Switzerland compared to a counterfactual scenario without BBR. Second, I conduct growth accounting with a neoclassical growth model, finding that the increase in Switzerland's growth is due to the increase in Total Factor Productivity (TFP), which includes institutional changes such as the adoption of the BBR, rather than changes in labor or capital accumulation. Third, I build an endogenous growth model with a government making inefficient decisions for political reasons. I find that by reducing public debt, the BBR tempers the "crowding-out effect of debt" and frees up resources for private investment in R&D. Additionally, by reducing the service of the debt, it also frees up resources for public investment in R&D. These investments, in turn, foster economic growth through their effect on TFP. The model calibrated to Switzerland shows that the long-term yearly growth effect of the BBR is 1.27 basis points, which compounds to a 3% GDP gain after 30 years.

JEL Classification: E62, H63, O43, O47

Keywords: Balanced Budget Rule, Public debt, Economic growth

The purpose of the AfCFTA is to reduce trade barriers for greater integration between African countries. WAEMU, having historically had its main trading partners outside Africa, will have to trade more within the continent. This paper identifies African countries with which WAEMU could increase its trade, studies the implications of such an increase on macroeconomic stability, before proposing a monetary policy orientation to minimize the impact of external shocks. To do so, we develop a new approach to detect the trade expansion potential between two economies. This approach, applied to WAEMU countries using the Harmonized System's detailed four-digit product classification, over the period 1996 to 2016, reveals that South Africa, Egypt, Morocco, Nigeria, Tunisia, Kenya and Ghana are the countries with the highest potential for trade expansion with WAEMU. With the AfCFTA, WAEMU could increase its imports by more than 12% on average with each of the African partners listed above. This figure reaches 32% for South Africa, the first potential partner. Using a new Keynesian model in an open economy, calibrated to WAEMU, we simulate several trade integration scenarios, targeted at the partners identified above. We find that greater integration with these countries will increase the transmission of price and production shocks from African partners to WAEMU economy. The Central Bank (BCEAO) within a framework of an optimal monetary policy should, in addition to inflation, react more to variations in the effective nominal exchange rate. Based on these results, the paper makes some recommendations for trade and monetary policies.

> JEL Classification: E43, E52, E58, F13, F15, F17, R13 Keywords: AfCFTA, WAEMU, BCEAO, free trade, monetary policy

REFERENCES

Guillaume Sublet (Advisor), Assistant Professor, Department of Economics, Université de Montréal 3150, Jean-Brillant street Montréal, QC, H3C 3J7, Canada, Email: guillaume.sublet@umontreal.ca , Website

Emanuela Cardia, Full Professor, Department of Economics, Université de Montréal 3150, Jean-Brillant Street Montreal, QC, H3C 3J7, Canada Tel: + 1 514 343 6111 #42831, Email: emanuela.cardia@umontreal.ca, Google Scholar

Immo Schott, Senior Economist, Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, Email: immoschott@gmail.com, Website